A racing second hand, a shooting comet, a wind-up doll, and a crowd!
،عقرب دقائق مسرِع، مُذنّب ساقط دمية آلية الخروج، وحشد ناس
Mystery-solving logic drenches the walls of dry hearts!
تبلل الاستنتاجات المفككة للغموض أسوار القلوب الجافة
Today's case is the first original TV 2-parter!
قضيّة اليوم هي أوّل حلقة تلفزية أصلية بجزأين
He sees the single truth for what it is,
يرى الحقيقة الواحدة
and looks like a kid but has the mind of an adult!
يحمل مظهر طفل، لكنّ عقله عقل بالغ
His name? Detective Conan!
!اسمه المتحرّي كونان
Mayor! Hurry!
!حضرة العمدة! أسرع
What is that?
ما هذه؟
Did last night's storm carry it here?
أجرفتها عاصفة البارحة إلى هنا؟
That's!
...تـ-تلك
Ryujin-Maru
ريوجين مارو
Hey! Isn't that the boat that was lost seven years ago?!
أليس ذاك القارب الذي فُقد في العاصفة قبل 7 أعوام؟
Get out there!
!جهّزوا القوارب
Right!
!حاضر
There was 1 billion yen in gold on that ship...
كان يوجد ذهب يُعادل مليار ينّ على متنه وفقما أذكر
Well?
كيف الأمر؟
There's nothing onboard!
لا يوجد شيء على متنه
That can't be! Where did all the gold go?!
مُحال! أين اختفى الذهب؟
Why do you suppose it turned up only now?
لمَ ظهرت الآن بعد كلّ ذاك الوقت؟
It's almost like a ghost ship.
كأنّها سفينة أشباح
Ghost?!
أ-أشباح؟
Could it be the Suigun curse?!
!أيمكن أنّها لعنة سويغون؟
You fools! There is no curse! It's just a dumb superstition!
!أحمق! لا وجود للعنات !إنّها مجرد خرافات سخيفة
The Ghost Ship Murder Case (Part 1)
(جريمة قتل سفينة الأشباح (الجزء الأوّل
We'll land on Shikishima in three hours.
سنصل جزيرة شيكي في قرابة 3 ساعات
We greatly appreciate
نقدّر قطعك الطريق الطويل
to give a lecture!
لإقامة محاضرة لنا
And it certainly is a long way!
إنّه طريق طويل بالفعل
Say, Kinoshita-san!
أخبرني يا كينوشيتا-سان
I hear a ship that went missing with 1 billion yen in gold onboard
سمعتُ أنّ سفينةً فُقدت قبل 7 أعوام وعلى متنها ما يعادل مليار ينّ ذهباً
recently turned up!
!قد ظهرت مؤخراً
Yes! People on the island think it's a ghost ship!
أجل! يظنّ أهل الجزيرة أنّها سفينة أشباح
But the money never turned up?
لكنّكم لم تجدوا الذهب؟
No. We're not even sure there really was any onboard.
كلا، لم نعد متأكدين إن كان موجوداً على متنها بالأصل الآن
The mayor is just glad that the town has garnered a lot of attention.
العُمدة مسرور لمجرّد جذب البلدة الكثير من الاهتمام بسبب السفينة
A ghost ship garnering attention?
سفينة أشباح تجذب الاهتمام؟
Of course! And that's not all!
بالطبع! وهذا ليس كلّ شيء
Inviting someone so famous is another way of gaining prestige!
دعوه شخص بمثل شهرتك هي طريقة أخرى لكسب الاعتبار
My reputation extends this far?!
تصل سمعتي هذه الأرجاء؟
But of course!
بالطبع
All of Japan knows about the great detective Kogoro Mori-san--
...كلّ من في اليابان يعرف المتحرّي العظيم موري-سان
Who's he?
من ذاك الشخص؟
He works for a Tokyo travel agency.
يعمل لوكالة سفر في طوكيو
He wants to create a tour centered around the ghost ship.
يريد إقامة جولة تتمحور حول سفينة الأشباح
Shikishima Island
جزيرة شيكي
It's Detective Mori!
!إنّه المتحرّي موري
Welcome, Kogoro Mori-sensei!!
!مرحباً بك يا موري كوغورو سينسي
It's really him!
!هو حقّاً
Welcome!
مرحباً
What a warm welcome!
!يا للترحيب الحافل
Mori-sensei! Thank you for coming all this way!
!موري سينسي! شكراً لقطعك كلّ الطريق الطويل
I'm Mayor Mikami!
أنا العمدة ميكامي
Thanks!
شكراً لكم
Is this lame guy really famous?
أهذا المُسن السخيف مشهور حقّاً؟
I thought you would've been a lot cooler.
ظننتُك ستكون أكثر روعة إن كنت متحرّياً معروفاً
What'd you say, kid?!
!ماذا قلتِ يا طفلة؟
Suzu-kun! Don't be rude to Daddy's guest!
!سوزو! لا تتكلمي بفظاظة مع ضيف أبيك
What a lovely daughter you have!
!يا للابنة الظريفة
What?
ماذا؟
What's your name?!
ما اسمك؟
Conan. Conan Edogawa.
كونان، إيدوغاوا كونان
That's a weird name. Is that the trend in Tokyo?
اسمٌ غريب، أهو شعبيّ في طوكيو؟
Leave me alone.
دعيني وشأني
Well, whatever.
لا يهم
I'm Suzu Mikami! It looks like I'm a little older than you!
(ميكامي سوزو (7 ابنة العمدة ميكامي
Being with younger people is trendy!
!مرافقة الأصغر سنّاً أمر شعبيّ مؤخراً
Move!
ابتعد
This is the travel agent--
...هذا من وكالة
I'm Uehara from Toto Travel Agency. Nice to meet you.
(أويهارا ياسو (44 موظّف مبيعات في وكالة توتو للسفر
Likewise! We'll help in any way to bring tourists here!
مرحباً! سنساعد بأيّ طريقة لجلب السيّاح هنا
Where is the ghost ship?
أين سفينة الأشباح؟
Here she is!
ها هي
I'll show you around!
سأرشدك
No thanks. I'll look for myself.
لا داعي، سأتفقدها بنفسي
This ship was on the ocean floor for years
كانت هذه السفينة في قاع المحيط لأعوام
but only has barnacles on its underside.
لكن لا يوجد سوى قشريات بحرية أسفلها
You dummy! It's a ghost ship!
!أحمق! إنّها سفينة أشباح
Talk about unscientific...
...ليس علميّاً أبداً
Lighthouse Keeper - Koji Hamada (42)
(42) كوجي هامادا حارس المنارة
Great Detective Kogoro Mori Lecture
محاضرة المتحرّي العظيم موري كوغورو
Here, Mori-sensei! There's still time until the lecture!
تفضّل يا موري سينسي! لا يزال أمامنا وقت قبل المحاضرة
Thanks!
!شكراً
Delicious!
!لذيذ
These cooked turban shells are delicious!
محّار العمامة المطهو هذا طيّب المذاق، صحيح؟
They sure are!
أجل
Say, after the lecture, I'd like to ask for your help...
بالمناسبة يا سينسي، أريد طلب مساعدتك في أمر بعد المحاضرة
You want me to find where the Ryujin-Maru sank?
تريدني أن أجد موقع غرق ريوجين مارو... صحيح؟
Such perceptiveness! I think it sank near this island.
يا للفطنة! أظنّها غرقت بالقرب من الجزيرة
If we just knew where, we could locate the missing gold!
إذا عرفنا المكان، يمكننا العثور على الذهب المفقود
But if it were recovered, it wouldn't belong to you.
لكن إذا عثرتم عليه فلن يكون لكم
The government would come to collect it.
ستأتي الحكومة وتأخذه
But wouldn't we be entitled to 10% of it?
لكن ألا يحقّ لنا 10% على الأقل؟
Maybe, but...
...ر-ربما، لكن
Please! Mori-sensei!
!أرجوك يا موري سينسي
Sorry! No famous detective would ever go treasure hunting--
أرفض! لن يُنقص متحرٍّ عظيم من مقامه ...للعب لعبة بحث عن كنز
How about 10% of the island's reward money?
سنعطيك 10% من حصّة الجزيرة
You have a deal!
!موافق
Thank you!
!شكراً جزيلاً
Kinoshita! Give him the details.
كينوشيتا! أعطه التفاصيل
Certainly.
حاضر
It happened on a stormy night seven years ago.
وقع الأمر قبل 7 أعوام في ليلة عاصفة
We received an SOS from the Ryujin-Maru about 1 km offshore.
وصلنا نداء استغاثة من ريوجين مارو على بعد كيلومتر واحد من الشاطئ
However, the signal disappeared as a rescue crew headed for it,
لكنّ الإشارة اختفت فجأةً بعدما توجّه طاقم إنقاذ لها
and the next day, only the owner's body washed ashore.
وفي اليوم التالي جرفت الأمواج جثّة المالك للشاطئ فحسب
No debris was ever found, much less the gold.
لم نعثر على أيّ آثار حطام، دون ذكر الذهب
Whose gold was this?
من كان صاحب الذهب؟
The ship's owner's. He was going to be arrested for tax evasion
مالك السفينة، كان سيُعتقل للتهرّب من الضرائب
so he converted his entire fortune into gold and was on his way
فحوّل كل ثروته لذهب وكان في طريقه
out of the country.
لمغادرة البلاد
I see.
هكذا إذاً
Very well! I, Kogoro Mori, shall locate the gold for you!
حسنٌ، سأقوم أنا موري كوغورو بالبحث !عن مكان الذهب لكم
Thank you very much!
!شكراً جزيلاً
I don't know about this lecture thing.
هل سيمضي أمر المحاضرة هذا على ما يرام؟
Isn't he just gonna humiliate himself?
ألن يحرج نفسه وحسب؟
Suigun Artifact Museum
متحف أثريات سويغون
The general's armor...
...درع القائد
Interesting?
أتجده مثيراً للاهتمام؟
Yeah! There's so much rare stuff!
!نعم! توجد أشياء نادرة كثيرة
Yes, it's this island's cultural heritage.
أجل، إنّه ميراث الجزيرة الثقافي
Four-hundred years ago, the Suigun escaped here after being defeated
قبل 400 عام، هرب سويغون إلى هنا
in a large battle.
بعد خسارته في معركة كبيرة
But the islanders wanted the reward money for their heads
لكنّ أهل الجزيرة أرادوا مال الجائزة على رأسه
and attacked the wounded Suigun.
وهاجموا سويغون المُصاب
They eventually drove them into a remote cave and killed them all.
دفعوه ورجاله لكهف معزول وقتلوهم جميعاً
Various bad things have occurred ever since.
حدثت العديد من الأمور السيّئة مُذ آنذاك
Like a curse?
كاللعنة؟
Yes. So a shrine was built in the cave to quiet the Suigun's spirits.
أجل، لذا بُني ضريح في الكهف لتهدئة روح سويغون
But aren't curses just superstitions?
لكن أليست اللعنات مجرد خرافات؟
No, that's not the case.
كلا، ليس صحيحاً
Many people who live near the cave have seen armor-clad ghosts,
رأى العديد من الناس الذين يعيشون قرب الكهف أشباحاً ترتدي درعاً
and eerie groans can be heard coming from the cave's depths.
ويمكنك سماع أنين مُخيف من أعماق الكهف
I think it was about five years ago
أظنّ الحادثة كانت قبل 5 أعوام
when a university professor studying the Suigun visited.
عندما أتى بروفسور جامعيّ هنا لدراسة سويغون
He ignored the islanders' warnings and went to examine the cave.
تجاهل تحذيرات أهل الجزيرة وذهب لفحص الكهف
But two or three nights later...
...وبعد ليلتين إلى ثلاث
And that professor?!
وذاك البروفسور؟
Yes. It was never confirmed, but he was never seen again.
أجل، لم يُؤكد الأمر... لكنه أصبح مفقوداً مُذ آنذاك
Nobody dares go near that cave anymore.
لم يعد هناك من يجرؤ على الاقتراب من الكهف الآن
Believing that in this day and age is why you get laughed at!
تصديق هذا الكلام في زماننا هو ما يجعل الآخرين يضحكون عليك
Young lady!
سيّدتي الصغيرة
Daddy said the professor checked the cave but probably left
قال أبي أنّ البروفسور فحص الكهف لكنّه غادر غالباً
'cause he didn't find anything.
لأنّه لم يجد شيئاً داخله
Let's go, Conan-kun! I'll show you a great place!
!هيّا بنا يا كونان-كن! سأريك مكاناً رائعاً
Wait!
!ا-انتظري
Where are we going?
أين نذهب؟
We can sneak backstage from here! Best seats in the house!
!يمكننا التسلل لوراء الكواليس من هنا إنّها أفضل مقاعد
What's with him?!
ما خطبه؟
Who is that?
من ذاك الشخص؟
Hamada, the lighthouse keeper. He's really weird!
حارس المنارة هامادا، إنّه شخص غريب الأطوار
Weird?
غريب الأطوار؟
He hardly hangs out with anyone, and he always goes to that cave.
لا يتسكّع مع أهل الجزيرة، ويذهب دائماً لكهف سويغون الذي يتفاداه الجميع
Long time, no see, Aoki.
لم أرك منذ وقت طويل يا آوكي
Don't pretend you don't recognize me.
لا تتظاهر أنّك نسيت... وجهي هذا
What are you talking about? I'm Hamada, the lighthouse keeper!
ما-ما الذي تتكلم عنه؟ أنا حارس المنارة هامادا
Why, you!
!أيّها الوغد
You have the wrong person! Let go!
!لستُ من تظن! دعني
I'll tear that face of yours off, Aoki!
سأخلع وجهك هذا يا آوكي
Now then, here is the peerless Detective Kogoro Mori-sensei!
!إذاً، ها هو المتحرّي العظيم موري كوغورو سينسي
You're too kind!
!شكراً، شكراً
Will he be all right drunk like that?
هل سيكون بخير وهو ثمل هكذا؟
How lame...
...بائس
He appears to be rather nervous!
...يبدو أنّه متوتر قليلاً
Let's have him break the celebration ball in honor of his visit!
!لنجعله يفتح كرة الاحتفال شرفاً بقدومه
Whenever you're ready!
!تفضّل يا سينسي
Huh?
ماذا؟
What's that smell?
...هذه الرائحة
It's gasoline!
!إنّه... بنزين
Old man!
!يا عمّ
What on earth?!
ما هذا؟
Dad!
!أبي
Hot! Hot!
!نار! نار
It's the curse! The Suigun curse!
!إنّها اللعنة! لعنة سويغون-ساما
Wait!
!أ-أنتم
Ah. That string was modified to ignite the gasoline inside.
فهمت، عُدّل الخيط بحيث يشعل البنزين داخل الكرة عندما يُسحب
The target being... the old man.
والهدف... كان العمّ
In which case, the ones most suspect are...
...ما يعني أنّ الأشخاص الأكثر شبهة
...Hamada-san, who left out the back door,
هم هامادا-سان الذي خرج من الباب الخلفيّ
and the man he got in an argument with, Uehara-san.
وأويهارا-سان من وكالة السفر الذي تشاجر معه
Could it have something to do with the ghost ship?!
أيمكن أنّ للأمر علاقة بسفينة الأشباح؟
Mayor! What's the meaning of this!
!حضرة العمدة! ما معنى هذا؟
I only survived because I'm so well-trained!
نجوتُ لأنّي مُدرّب بعناية فقط
My deepest apologies for getting you involved in such an accident!
أقدّم خالص اعتذاري! توّرطك في هذه !الحادثة من شديد أسفي
Accident?! Someone clearly planned that!
حادثة؟ كانت من تخطيط أحد بكلّ وضوح
No, sparks from a short circuit just happened to ignite
...كلا، أشعلت شرارات من دائرة قصر
a nearby gas container--
حاوية بنزين في الجوار
But...
...لكن
Listen to me. It was an accident.
كانت حادثة، لا شكّ في الأمر
You sure you just don't want a police incident?
ألا تريد تفادي تدخل الشرطة وحسب؟
Weren't gonna turn the gold over if you found it, were you?
أي لم تنو تسليم الذهب إذا وجدته، صحيح؟
But you'd have no choice if the mainland police showed up.
لكنك لن تمتلك خياراً إن أتت شرطة البرّ الرئيسي
Mori-san! You just need to keep quiet and find the gold!
موري-سان! عليك البقاء صامتاً والعثور على الذهب وحسب
What was that?!
!ماذا؟
Defy me and there's no guarantee you'll leave the island unharmed.
عارضني ولا ضمان لأن تغادر هذه الجزيرة سليماً
You can't threaten me!
!لا يمكنك تهديدي
You can't take the ferry without my authorization.
لا تستطيع صعود العبّارة دون إذني
Well, take your time to think it over tonight.
حسناً، خذ وقتك بالتفكير الليلة
Damn him!
!تبّاً
Looks like we came to a pretty bad island...
يبدو أنّنا أتينا لجزيرة فظيعة
Kinoshita-san...
كينوشيتا-سان
I apologize. The mayor seems to only care about finding the gold
آسف، يبدو أنّ العمدة مهتم بالعثور على الذهب فقط
and turning the island into a tourist attraction.
وتحويل الجزيرة لنقطة سياحية
He's a selfish bastard!
!وغد أنانيّ
But don't worry.
لكن لا تقلقوا
I'll take you back to the mainland anyway.
سآخذكم للبرّ الرئيسي بأيّ حال
Luckily, I can prepare a small fishing boat.
يمكنني تحضير قارب صيد صغير لحسن الحظ
That's great!
!هذا رائع
No! I refuse to go!
!كلا! أرفض التحرّك من هنا
Dad?!
أبي؟
Inadvisable!
!لا يمكنك
You may be harmed if you stay!
!قد يصيبك الأذى إن بقيت
No self-respecting detective would dare run away now!
لا مُتحرٍّ مرموق ذي احترام !قد يهرب بعد سماع كلام كهذا
Well said, old man!
أحسنت القول يا عمّ
Kinoshita-san!
كينوشيتا-سان
What is Hamada-san like?
كيف هو هامادا-سان بالضبط؟
You mean the lighthouse keeper?
تقصد حارس المنارة؟
Yeah.
أجل
I don't know; he's not from here.
لا أدري، ليس من أهل الجزيرة
He came here a while after the Ryujin-Maru incident
أتى بعد حادثة ريوجين مارو بفترة
and said he was looking for work.
وقال أنّه يبحث عن عمل
There was no one working the lighthouse, so he took that job.
لم يكن هناك من يعمل في المنارة فأخذ ذاك العمل
Did Hamada do something?
هل قام هامادا بشيء؟
No! I just thought he seemed strange!
لا! بدا لي غريباً قليلاً فقط
See you later!
!إلى اللقاء
Is that Hamada-i?
أذاك هامادا-سان؟
It's me!
!إنّها أنا
Don't scare me!
!لا تخيفيني
How rude! You should thank me for following you late at night!
ما خطبك؟! عليك أن تكون ممتناً للحاقي بك !وأنت طفل يمشي بمفرده آخر الليل
Wait!
مهلك
Wait, we're not that close of friends yet--
...انتظر، لسنا مقرّبين لذاك الحدّ بعد
Uehara-san?
أويهارا-سان؟
So he was that person up there?
كان هو الشخص في الأعلى إذاً؟
What the...
ما-ما هذا؟
That person was searching the place?
كان ذاك الرجل يفتّش المكان
That smell!
!هذه الرائحة
It's gasoline. Yet there are no cars or motorcycles here.
بنزين، رغم أنّ لا سيّارات أو درّاجات نارية هنا
It's light.
خفيف
So it was Hamada-san who tried to kill him!
كان هامادا-سان من حاول قتل العمّ إذاً؟
Conan! Don't run off!
!كونان! لا تذهب بمفردك
What was he doing up here?!
ماذا كان يفعل هنا؟
A telescope?
منظار؟
Forget it. There's nothing to see.
انسَ الأمر، لا شيء لتراه
It's pointed at the mountains. They'd be boring to look at.
فهو موجّه نحو الجبال، من الممل النظر عبره
That's strange. A lighthouse telescope should be pointing out to sea.
غريب، من المُفترض أن يكون منظار المنارة موجّه نحو البحر
But this one is fixed toward the mountains!
لكن هذا مثبّت نحو الجبال
What is it?
ما الخطب؟
'Ryujin-Maru'?
ريوجين مارو؟
No question about it! Hamada-san is connected to the Ryujin-Maru!
!لا شكّ في الأمر، لهامادا-سان علاقة بريوجين مارو
And there's something he doesn't want investigated,
وهناك شيء لا يريده أن يُكشف بشأنه
so he tried to kill the old man...
...لذا حاول قتل العمّ
Oh no! The old man and Ran!
!كلا! العمّ وران
Hold on!
!انتظر
Morning already?
حلّ الصباح بهذه السرعة؟
Who are you?!
!مـ-من أنت؟
What's going on--
...ما الذي
Ran! Stay away!
!ران! ابتعدي
Get back here, you!
!انتظر أيّها الوغد
Dad!
!أبي
Conan-kun?!
كونان-كن؟
Get back here!
!أيّها الوغد! مكانك
It's hard to run with my sore butt!
!من الصعب الركض بألم مؤخرتي
I got you now!
!حاصرتك الآن
Where did you go?! I was so worried!
!أين كنت؟! شعرتُ بقلق شديد
Did something happen?!
أحصل أمرٌ ما؟
Dad was attacked by a Suigun!
!تعرّض أبي للهجوم من قِبل شبح سويغون
What?!
!ماذا؟
What's that?!
ما هذا؟
The alarm bell by the port!
جرس تنبيه الميناء
They ring it whenever something happens!
يقومون بطرقه عند وقوع أمرٍ ما
Don't tell me--
...أيمكن
Conan-kun!
!كونان-كن
Come on, already!
!يا إلهي
Hey! Did something happen?!
!أوقع أمرٌ ما؟
Help!
!ساعدوني
This is some sort of mistake!
!هذا خطأٌ ما
The old man?!
العمّ؟
Dad!
!أبي
What on earth is going on?!
!ما الذي يجري؟
That detective killed Hamada, the lighthouse keeper!
قتل ذاك المتحرّي حارس المنارة هامادا
What?!
!ماذا؟
Dad did?!
!أبي؟
Check for yourself if you think we're lying!
!انظروا بأنفسكم إذا ظننتمونا نكذب
When we arrived on the scene, the detective was unconscious
عدما وصلنا للمكان كان هذا المتحرّي فاقداً للوعي
and the victim was dead!
والضحيّة بهذه الحالة
Believe me! I didn't do it!
!صدّقوني! لم أكن الفاعل
You'll pay!
!ستدفع الثمن
The ghosts got mad because an outsider was poking around!
غضب سويغون-ساما بسبب عبث !دخيل في الأرجاء
He would never do something like this!
لن يُقدم العمّ على شيء كهذا مُطلقاً
But given the situation!
...لكن... في هذه الظروف
Kinoshita-san!
!كينوشيتا-سان
The ghosts are mad!
!سويغون-ساما غاضب
A suicide?!
انتحار؟
No, this was no suicide! In which case, the killer is--
...كلا، لم يكن انتحاراً! ما يعني أنّ القاتل
The Ghost Ship Murder Case (Part 2)
(جريمة قتل سفينة الأشباح (الجزء الثاني
On the next Conan--
في الحلقة القادمة من كونان
Next Conan's Hint:
تلميح الحلقة القادمة
Gunshot Wound.
جرح طلقة نارية
Next episode the case takes a surprising turn.
يحصل تطوّر غير متوقّع !في الحلقة القادمة
Heh, heh, heh. I'm the culprit.
!المجرم هو أنا
It's not you, Genta.
!ليس أنت